Inventory of the James Addison Logan Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
James Addison Logan Papers
1913-1924
56013
Logan, James Addison, 1879-1930.
17 manuscript boxes (6.8 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Contains correspondence, memoranda, and reports that reflect the prevalent international situation during and after World War I. They relate to the U.S. war effort, conditions of prisoners of war, the Paris Peace Conference, postwar reconstruction in Europe, and war reparations.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1930
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biography Note
1879 November 11 Born, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania
1901 Joined U.S. Army as captain
1911? Student, Haverford College, Pennsylvania
1912 Graduated, Army War College
1914 September - 1917 June Chief, U.S. military mission with French army
1919 December - 1923 July 1 Assistant U.S. unofficial delegate to Reparation Commission
1921 U.S. unofficial representative, London conference of prime ministers
1921 June - 1923 June Adviser, American Relief Administration in connection with Russian relief
1922 July 15 Resigned from U.S. Army
1923 August 1 - 1925 May 31 U.S. unofficial delegate to the Reparation Commission
1925 Attended finance ministers' conference, Paris, France LL.D., Haverford College, Pennsylvania
1925 June Associated with Dillon, Read & Company
1930 October 27 Died, Protestant Home, Montgomery County, Pennsylvania
Scope and Content of Collection
The papers of James Addison Logan consist of correspondence, memoranda, and reports that reflect the prevalent international situation during and after World War I. They relate to the U.S. war effort, conditions of prisoners of war, the Paris Peace Conference, postwar reconstruction in Europe, and war reparations.
Correspondence constitutes the bulk of the materials. It is organized in two main groups, personal and secret. The secret letters deal with the more complex postwar issues. Many of the secret letters are incorporated in the bound volumes.
The papers were acquired in 1930.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Subjects
Allied and Associated Powers (1914-1920) Supreme Economic Council.; Inter-Allied Commission for Reparations.; United States. Army.; Paris Peace Conference (1919-1920); Prisoners of war.; Reconstruction (1914-1939)--Europe.; World War, 1914-1918--Economic aspects.; World War, 1914-1918--Peace.; World War, 1914-1918--Prisoners and prisons.; World War, 1914-1918--Reparations.; World War, 1914-1918--United States.
Container List
- Personal Correspondence (Box 1)
  - 1919
    - January-February (Folder 1: 1-2)
    - May- December (Folder 1: 3-10)
  - 1920
    - January (Folder 1: 11-22)
  - 1921
    - January-March (Folder 1: 23-25)
    - April-December (Box-folder 2: 1-9)
  - 1922
    - January-April (Folder 2: 10-13)
    - May- December (Box-folder 3: 1-8)
  - 1923 (Box 4)
    - January-October (Folder 4: 1-10)
    - November- December (Box-folder 5: 1-2)
  - 1924
    - January- October (Folder 5: 3-12)
  - Polish finance and Poland-U.S. trade, 1920 November 18 - December 7 (Folder 5: 13)
  - Secret Correspondence., See also bound volumes (Box 6)
    - 1922 (Folder 6: 1-2)
    - 1923 (Folder 6: 3-4)
    - 1923 September - 1925 February (Box-folder 7: 1)
- Bound volumes
  - Supreme Economic Council--Minutes of proceedings--Volumes I and II, 1919 February - May.; See also box 15 (Folder 7: 2)
  - Miscellaneous documents in connection with treaties of peace--Volume I, 1919 June 28 (Folder 7: 3)
  - Secret letters
    - Volume I, 1918 November 11 - 1923 November 23. (Folder 7: 4)
      Chronological statement of the sequence of events bearing on reparation from the armistice of November 11, 1918, until the creation of the Dawes Committee, November 23, 1923
    - Volume II, undated (Box-folder 8: 1)
    - Volume III, Volume III, 1918 November 11 - 1921 February 24. (Folder 8: 2)
      Reparation question
    - Volume IV, 1921 February 24 - March 11 (Box-folder 8: 3)
    - Volume V, 1921 March 11 - 1922 February 17 (Box-folder 9: 1)
    - Volume VI, 1922 February 17 - June 26 (Folder 9: 2)
    - Volume VII, 1922 June 26 - December 22 (Box-folder 10: 1)
    - Volume VIII, 1922 December 22 - 1923 March 9 (Folder 10: 2)
    - Volume IX, 1923 March 9 - September 6 (Box-folder 11: 1)
    - Volume X, 1923 September 6 - 1924 April 1 (Folder 11: 2)
- Commission des Réparation (Box 12)
  - Extraits des Protocoles des Correspondences Echangees et du Traite de Paix Entre les Puissances Alliées et Associées et L'Allemagne, undated (Folder 12: 1)
  - Minutes of proceedings, 1919 (Folder 12: 2)
  - Documentary history of the treaty of peace between the Allied and associated powers and Germany, undated (Folder 12: 3)
- Reports following the entry of the United States into the World War I--Ports of debarkation, American military cooperation with France, French and American military missions, liaison, military information, and utilization of Red Cross units, 1917 (Box-folder 13: 1-3)
- Reports on prisoners of war, the Hague Conference, and the International Red Cross, 1915 (Folder 13: 4)
- Reports on politico-military subjects and censorship, 1914 September - 1917 April (Box-folder 14: 1-3)
- Report on Serbia in the European War, 1913-1916 (Folder 14: 4)
- 1 Supreme Economic Council--Minutes of proceedings., See also box 7 (Box 15)
  - Volumes III-V, 1919 June - July (Folder 15: 1)
  - Volumes VI and VII, 1919 October - 1920 February (Folder 15: 2)
- Observations
  - German delegation on conditions of peace, undated (Folder 15: 3)
  - Bulgarian delegation on conditions of peace with Bulgaria and reply of the Allies and associated powers, 1919 (Box-folder 16: 1)
- Traité de Paix Entre les Puissances Alliées et Associées et L'Allemagne et Protocole signés a Versailles, 1919 June 28 (Folder 16: 2)
- Traité de Paix Entre les Puissances Alliées et Associées et L'Autriche Protocole et Déclarations Signés à Saint-Germain-en-Laye, 1919 September 10 (Folder 16: 3)
- Traité de Paix Entre les Puissances Alliées et Associées et la Bulgarie Protocole et Déclarations Signés à Neuilly-Sur-Seine, 1919 November 27 (Box-folder 17: 1)
- Traité de Paix Entre les Puissances Alliées et Associées et la Hongrie Protocole et Déclaration (Trianon), 1920 June 4 (Folder 17: 2)
- Personal papers, Paris, 1910-1920 (Folder 17: 3)
- Shoe string adventurers, 1921 January - March. (Folder 17: 4)
  Correspondence
- Supreme Economic Council, 1919 December - 1921 April. (Folder 17: 5)